Thomas A. Pickett Papers, Inclusive: 1944-1952, undated, Bulk: 1944-1952
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
Thomas A. Pickett Papers
Inclusive: 1944-1952, undated, Bulk: 1944-1952
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials http://www.baylor.edu/lib/bcpm/
27
Pickett, Thomas Augustus
6 document boxes.
The Thomas A. Pickett Papers mostly span the years 1945-1952, and were compiled during Pickett's career as a U.S. Representative for the 7th Congressional District of Texas. They include campaign materials, legislative records, tidelands materials, and personal papers.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Thomas A. Pickett was born on August 14, 1906, in Travis, Falls County, Texas. He lived briefly in Iola and then moved to Palestine, Texas with his family in 1913. He attended public schools there and graduated from Palestine High School in 1923. Pickett then attended Conway's Business College and worked for one year in his father's law office. He attended the University of Texas from 1924 to 1928. While in his first year at the university, he was elected freshman class president.
Following graduation, Pickett was admitted to the state bar and began practice in Palestine in 1929. Pickett served as Anderson County Attorney from 1931 until 1935. Next, he served as district attorney for the 3rd Judicial District from 1935 to 1945.
In his last year of district attorney, Pickett turned towards politics and ran for a seat in the House of Representatives. Having successfully, unseated incumbent Nat Patton in the Democratic primary, Pickett went on to defeat Republican J. Perrin Willis in the general election. He began his term as member of Congress, representing Texas' 7th District on January 3, 1945. Pickett's political successes continued in the subsequent elections of 1946, 1948, and 1950. Each time, running unopposed. In Congress, Pickett served on the House Public Works, Veterans Affairs, and Administration committees.
Pickett resigned from office on June 30, 1952 and was succeeded by John Dowdy in September 1952.
After public office, Pickett served as vice-president of the National Coal Association from 1952 until 1961 and the Association of American Railroads from 1961 to 1968. Pickett later moved to Florida in 1968.
Pickett died on June 7, 1980, in Leesburg, Florida.
Scope and Content
Material is present from Pickett's tenure as a United States Representative for the 7th Texas Congressional District. Items represent Pickett's service in the 79th through the 82nd Congresses. In his House tenure, Pickett served on the Foreign Affairs Committee, the House Administration Committee, and the Judiciary Committee. The collection documents Pickett's congressional campaigns, his legislative interests in the Tidelands case, public works projects on the Neches, Angelinas, and Trinity Rivers, and railroad bankruptcy and its impact on Anderson County, Texas.
Arrangement
The Thomas A. Pickett Papers came to Baylor Collection of Political Materials through the accession of the John V. Dowdy, Sr. Papers around 1972. John V. Dowdy, Sr. took Pickett's seat in the U. S. House of Representatives, 7th Congressional District, following Pickett's resignation in June 1952. The Pickett Papers were removed and processed as a separate collection.
After a 2012 addition to the collection, an updated topical arrangement was devised. There are four series: I. Campaigns II. Legislative III. Tidelands and IV. Personal. Within each series, material is arranged topically.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 27. Acquired 1972-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
"PICKETT, Thomas Augustus." Congressional Biographical Directory. bioguide.congress.gov (accessed December 4, 2013).
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Pickett, Thomas Augustus -- Archives.
Subjects
Legislators -- United States -- Archives.; Petroleum in submerged lands -- United States.; Railroad law -- United States.; Rivers -- Law and legislation -- Texas.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Legislative materials.; Speeches.
- Campaigns, 1944-1950, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  As a member of Congress from 1945 to 1952, Pickett ran in four successful campaigns. Items in this series include speech texts, radio spots, and press material.
  - General, 1944-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Opposition, 1944;1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Press, 1944-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Radio Spots, 1948; 1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Speeches, 1944; 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Topical, Korean War and Communism, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Legislative, 1945-1968; 2
  The Legislative series is the most robust series in the Pickett Papers and is arranged topically. From activity reports to his voting record, items reflects Pickett’s role as a representative of Texas’ 7th Congressional district. Casework documents individuals and veterans requesting assistance in obtaining pensions increases and disability compensation. Of note is a request for a Civil War Veteran's headstone. Foreign affairs include about foreign policy in a post-World War II era and aid to Korea. Public Works materials chronicle Pickett's support and work on projects such as Dams along the Neches-Angelina River, the Sabine Neches Waterway, and the need for flood control along the Trinity River. Also included is a proposal for the completion of the Rusk Charcoal Blast Furnace and Chemical Plant in Rusk, Texas, and the United States Department of the Interior. Also featured is Pickett’s legislation regarding printing of briefs for House of Representatives members about the steel seizure case. Pickett’s interest in the economic effects of railroad reorganization for the International-Great Northern Railroad Company (I.-G.N.) on his home district in Anderson County is included is present
  - General, 1944-1950; 1
    - Activity Reports, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Civil Rights, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Floor Statements, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Voting Record, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bills, 2
    - Communists, HR 5331, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - National Emergency, HJ Res 432, 460, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Personal Relief, HR 1264, 5347, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Private Property, HJ Res 470, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Servicemen’s Readjustment Act Amendment, HR 5884, 5885, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Steel Seizure Court Documents, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Taft-Hartley Act, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Foreign Affairs, 3
    - Aid, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Armed Forces in Foreign Countries, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Korea, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Speech, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Railroads, 4
    - House Judiciary Hearings, 1943; 1945; 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission, 1941; 1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Railroad Bankruptcy, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Railroad Bankruptcy, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Railroad Bankruptcy, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Palestine and Anderson County, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Projects, Dams, and Waterways, 5
    - Neches and Angelina Rivers, Blackburn Dam, Correspondence, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Neches and Angelina Rivers, Blackburn Dam, Press, 1946-1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Neches and Angelina Rivers, McGee Band, General, 1946-1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Neches and Angelina Rivers, McGee Bend, Press, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Neches and Angelina Rivers, Rockland Dam, Correspondence, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Neches and Angelina Rivers, Rockland Dam, Correspondence, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Neches and Angelina Rivers, Rockland Dam, Correspondence, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Neches and Angelina Rivers, Report, “Brief on behalf of Lower Neches Valley Authority,” Beaumont, Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Neches and Angelina Rivers, Speech, Water Conservation/Flood Control, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Rusk, Texas, Charcoal Blast Furnace, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Rusk, Texas, Hardwood Distillation, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Rusk, Texas, Iron Ore Deposits, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Sabine-Neches Waterway, General, 1939; 1949 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Sabine-Neches Waterway, Correspondence, 1945-1946; 1949 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Sabine-Neches Waterway, Hearings, 1938; 1941 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Sabine-Neches Waterway, Press, 1945-1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Trinity River, General, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Trinity River, Benbrook Dam, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Trinity River, Bills and Reports, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Trinity River, Correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Trinity River, Lower Middle Cedar Creek Watershed 1948 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Trinity River, Lower Reaches, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Trinity River, Upper Middle Cedar Creek Waterbed, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Tidelands, 1947-1949; 3
  Material relates to issue of submerged land rights in states and the ensuing Tidelands controversy and Supreme Court case. Publications, reports, and correspondence related to California and Texas Tidelands are present.
  - General, Bills, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - General, Map, Federally Owned Lands, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - General, News Clippings, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - General, Poem, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - General, Speech, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - California, General, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - California, Correspondence, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - California, Reports, “State Ownership of Submerged Lands: An Answer to the Federal Claims Asserted in the ‘tidelands’ Case of US v. California, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - California, Reports, “This Can Happen to Any State!” by Fred n. Howser, Attorney General of California, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - California, Supreme Court Case, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Texas, General, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Groups, Texas School Land Board, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Groups, Texas State Democratic Party, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Groups, Texas Water Conservation Association, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Publications, “A Handbook for Speakers and Local Bar Committees,” Tidelands Committee of the State Bar of Texas, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Texas, Publications, “Congress Again Considers Far-reaching Tidelands Oil Controversy,” Congressional Digest, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Publications, “Texas Tidelands: A Handbook for Speakers and Local Bar Committees,” Tidelands Committee of the State Bar of Texas, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Publications, “Title to Lands under Navigable Water,” Marquette Law Review, 1948 May (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Texas, “Truth about the Tidelands,” Sheridan Downey, US Senator, California, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Price Daniel, Attorney General of Texas, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Personal, 1944-1951, undated; 4
  Personal material features biographical information about Pickett including a resume and photograph. Miscellaneous personal correspondence is also present. Of note is Pickett’s “Century Vault Letter,” which was published in the San Antonio Express in 1949 and written by Pickett to readers 100 years in the future.
  - Biographical, 1951, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - “Century Vault Letter,” San Antonio Express, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1951 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - News Clippings (1 of 2), 1949-1951 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - News Clippings (2 of 2), 1949-1951 (Box 6, Folder 6)